CURRICULUM VITAE

Name: ALEXEY UGLOV

Email: alexey.ouglov@gmail.com (preferred)

Phone: +601139990951 (mobile), +60342653011 (landline)

Location: Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Senior linguist & professional translator with over 17 years of experience in translation, editing, proofreading, reviewing, copywriting and language teaching from English to Russian and vice versa. A quick learner who can absorb new ideas and communicate clearly and effectively with people from all social & professional backgrounds. Well mannered, articulate and fully aware of diversity and multicultural issues. Flexibility and ability to adapt to new challenges same time remaining aware of professional roles & boundaries.

Managerial Skills:

- Assessing needed skills and qualifications and evaluating job candidates.
- Building up a small-to-medium team for a specific task and defining job roles.
- Training and instructing team members, monitoring their performance and assessing results.

Data-handling Skills:

- Targeted data-mining.
- Research and analysis of obtained data.
- Presentation of results in demonstrative form.

• Web-support Skills:

- Web-content administration skills: monitoring, reviewing, moderating, and organizing.
- Solid experience in support of and interaction with users via live chat and email, handling user feedback.

• Translation-software Skills:

- Import/export of working files, translation, localization, spellcheck and punctuation check in translated text.
- Creation of new and opening of existing translation memories, their import/export in various formats, creation of translation memories based on aligning of bilingual texts
- Preliminary and on-demand analysis of translation projects using translation memories.
- Configuring of translation software packages.

• General Skills:

- Scrupulous attention to details coupled with clear vision of overall project/task and its separate parts.
- Analytical mindset, proven abilities in linguistic analysis and derivation of new inferential information.
- ❖ Active contribution of practical recommendations and appropriate solutions in jobrelated multi-party meetings & discussions targeted at resolving existing task/project issue.

OBJECTIVE

Would like to work for a successful and ambitious company that offers great opportunities for career development and progression.

AREAS OF EXPERTISE:

TRANSLATION, EDITING AND PROOFREADING FIELDS:

- Oil, Gas & Power Engineering (thermal & nuclear)
- Business & Economy (macro- & microeconomics, finance, advertising & marketing, logistics, personnel management and HR, public relations).
- ❖ IT & Internet (software, hardware, websites, data processing, patents/trademarks).
- ❖ Technical (machinery & equipment, mechanical & electrical engineering, technics & techniques, science & R&D, consumer electronics)
- Medical (medical equipment & facilities, research/therapy & care)
- Legal (civil law, contracts & agreements)
- Computer Games
- Movie Scripts/Subtitles & Television Broadcasts

INTERPRETATION, INTERBUSINESS / INTERCULTURAL COMMUNICATION COPYWRITING REVIEWING, LINGUISTIC CONSULTING LANGUAGE TEACHING, TUTORING

IT SKILLS

Operating Systems:

Windows, Linux Ubuntu

Programming Languages:

REALbasic/XOJO (for Windows, Mac, Linux & Web)

Other:

MS Office, translation/editing CAT-tool software packages – SDL Trados, ATRIL Deja Vu X2, Flash technology (using **SWiSHMax** software package), Web 3.0 technology (using **XOJO** software package), AutoCAD.

EDUCATION

Master's Degree in Engineering ("Heat and Power") at Ivanovo State Power University (1990 - 1995)

Master's Degree in Management at Ivanovo State Textile Academy (2001-2005)

WORK EXPERIENCE

CLIENT: GOOGLE, INC. (HYDERABAD, INDIA)

NOVEMBER 2011 – OCTOBER 2013

ROLE: SENIOR GEO CONTENT REVIEWER – RUSSIAN

- Administration (monitoring, reviewing, moderating, organizing) of web-content posted on a social-network portal (Russian locale), participation in the above-mentioned activity for other locales (Arabic, Thai and English) with the use of Google Translator.
- Update of specific sections of the portal based on daily and necessity-wise requirements.
- Support and interaction, providing administrative feedback to users' questions, requests and complaints.
- Handling user feedback regarding portal UI (user interface), functionality and content; coordinating and follow-up on it with technical department.
- Selection and appraisal of users as candidates for Power Users on the portal; building, training and instructing the team of external moderators on the rules, approaches and criteria of content moderation. Supervising, analyzing and presentation of team results, indication and correction of mistakes.
- Conduction of multiple various-purpose data-mining, research and analysis tasks related to user activities on the portal and follow-up on their results.
- Participating in multi-party video-conferencing discussions related to urgent and ongoing issues on the portal, brainstorming sessions and active contribution to the pool of recommendations and solutions targeted at resolving existing UI/functionality issues and promoting user activities on the portal.
- Formation of linguistic filters for automated premoderation (early nonallowed-content detection) system on the portal based on linguistic analysis of its content.
- Interaction and coordination with legal department to follow-up on content issues related to Russian legislation and portal rules & regulations.
- Facilitation and automation of regular and ad-hoc tasks by developing customized software in REALbasic (XOJO) programming language for Windows, Linux, Mac platforms & Web environment.
- Detection, testing, handling and elimination of spammers' and hackers' attacks, loopholes and vulnerabilities on the portal.

ROLE: LINGUISTIC EXPERT (FREELANCE)

SEPTEMBER 2008 – OCTOBER 2011

CLIENTS & PROJECTS (including but not limited to):

Microsoft • Sonosite • Steris • Sybron • Zoll • Abbott Diabetes Care • Advanced Medical Optics • Applied Biosystems • Janssen • NCAB Group • Novartis • Nuvelo • Dell • Nokia • Philips • Polycom • Seagate • Siemens • Sakhalin-2

- Translation, Editing, Proofreading (English <—> Russian) of text materials in various fields.
- Interpretation/ Interbusiness Intercultural Communication (English <—> Russian): negotiations, meetings, business talks, over-the-phone, via Skype.
- Reviewing/ Linguistic Consulting (Russian) on any written and oral materials related to Russian language.
- Selecting, appraising, building, supervising and controlling a team of translators (2-4 members) to ensure quality work and timely delivery.
- Tutorship to low-experienced translators regarding professional skills and approaches in their work.
- Copywriting (Russian): marketing and advertising materials related to imported goods and services.
- Language Teaching / Tutoring (Russian).
- Software development in REALbasic (XOJO) programming language for optimization and improvement of translation process.

CLIENT:

FEBRUARY 2008 - AUGUST 2008

DIGICAPTIONS INDIA PVT LTD (BANGALORE, INDIA)

ROLE: APPLIED LANGUAGE TECHNICIAN FOR SLAVONIC LANGUAGES (RUSSIAN, BULGARIAN, BELORUSSIAN, UKRAINIAN, SERBIAN)

- Review/Editing/Translation of subtitles for Russian-dubbed movies. Review of Russian-language content.
- Worked on proprietary software packages for processing of subtitles to dub movies.
- Contribution to the process of movie conversion from DVD to Blue-Ray format.
- Selection of Russian language speakers with appropriate linguistic and voice characteristics for participation in movie and advertisement dubbing into Russian.
- Participation in a project of synchronous written translation of Red-Carpet "Hot News" from live broadcast of Hollywood Oscar Awards.
- Parametrization of technical characteristics for proprietary software subtitle-processing package (identification of optimal coefficient providing for the best timeline matching of textual subtitles with voice dialogues).

ROLE: LINGUISTIC EXPERT (FREELANCE)

OCTOBER 2004 – JANUARY 2008

CLIENTS & PROJECTS (including but not limited to):

Microsoft • Sonosite • Steris • Sybron • Zoll • Abbott Diabetes Care • Advanced Medical Optics • Applied Biosystems • Janssen • Nuvelo • APC • Baxter • Gambro BCT • Hyperion • Novell • SeaGull • Synaptics

- Translation, editing, proofreading (English <--> Russian) of text materials in various fields.
- Interpretation/ Interbusiness Intercultural Communication (English <—> Russian): negotiations, meetings, business talks, over-the-phone, via Skype.
- Reviewing/ Linguistic Consulting (Russian) on any written and oral materials related to Russian language.
- Copywriting (Russian): marketing and advertising materials related to imported goods and services.
- Language Teaching / Tutoring (Russian).

CLIENT: RUSLAN, LTD (IVANOVO, RUSSIA) OCTOBER 2003 – SEPTEMBER 2004 ROLE: TRANSLATOR, INTERPRETER, EDITOR, PROOFREADER (ENGLISH <—> RUSSIAN)

- Translation of projects for globally known companies such as Microsoft, Novel, Oracle, APC, Polycom and others.
- Editing of translated material to ensure their high quality along with consistency of terminology, style and lexical structure across various parts of projects completed by different translators.
- Localization of translated and edited projects to ensure native feel and touch of localized materials.
- Proofreading of completed translation projects prepared for publishing either in paper or electronic format.
- Check-up and appraisal of translation tests made by candidates seeking a job in the company.
- Correction of encoding-related error in specialized translation package "Trados" that made its user interface completely visible and readable and allowed proper use of the software company-wide.
- Counseling and tutorship to colleagues on their translation and editing work.
- Consultation and expert advice on technical domains related to translation projects.

CLIENT:
DIAMECS ENGINEERING, LTD (IVANOVO, RUSSIA)

DECEMBER 2002 – SEPTEMBER 2003

ROLE: TRANSLATOR, EDITOR (ENGLISH <-> RUSSIAN)

- Translation of written materials on a number of technical and humanitarian subjects.
- Participation in large-scale projects as part of the team.
- Providing consultations for team-mates on technical aspects in translation projects.
- Counseling of junior team-mates on issues and problems in their translation work.

LANGUAGE SKILLS

Russian: Native (speaking/listening, writing/reading)
English: Expert Level (speaking/listening, writing/reading)

Belorussian: Intermediate Level (listening, reading), Basic Level (speaking, writing) **Ukrainian:** Intermediate Level (listening, reading), Basic Level (speaking, writing)

Bulgarian: Basic-to-Intermediate Level (reading), Basic Level (listening)

Serbian: Basic-to-Intermediate Level (reading)